hello everyone this is Frank defrays and
I'd like to welcome you to another week
of hollow talk for the week of December
20th 1999 and this will be the final
Holo talk show of this year uh we will
return once again after the new year uh
probably let me see if I can find my
calendar here
uh looks like
um
probably will be January 9th the week of
January 9th 2000 so I'd like to take
this opportunity to If you happen to
celebrate this holiday season to wish
you a happy holiday and hope that you'll
come back and tune in more Hollow talk
shows for the year 2000 I've got a
number of guests lined up
for interviews on the shows as well
to start off I'd like to thank many of
the listeners who offered to send in
past Hollow talk shows from this year
from
um fall on I had them in a folder on the
hard drive and I didn't have them backed
up like I have the other whole talk
shows backed up
and you know how it goes I grabbed that
folder took it down to the trash for
some reason and emptied that trash and
bye bye whole talk shows for the entire
season so far but thanks to a number of
of whole talk listeners I think we're
pretty close to having the entire season
rebuilt in fact one whole talk listener
just went ahead and put them all on
disks and shipped them to me which was
very nice so
thank you very much
I will give an update right after the
new year just in case one or two of them
are still missing and I will let you
know if any additional shows are needed
to fill that up and what I'll do over
the holidays go on to the archive page
and get all of the shows back up on the
archive page so that you can listen to
not only the shows from two years ago or
last year but all of the shows from this
season so far as well
moving on a few news items this is more
general interest I guess than news but
Bill Pugh who is the teacher who
had a hand in rewriting the new state
standards for communication Technologies
in the State of Florida having
holography written into that for next
school year
came up to Allentown to visit the studio
and do some work and we took a few of
his laser pointers and his laser diodes
and put them on the table he was having
difficulty getting getting images
and we wanted to test to see what the
trouble was so among a number of other
things that he was up here for as well
so we took the laser diodes and I set up
an interferometer and I found something
very very interesting and
he had an infiniter which is what Steve
Michael and I have been using for quite
some time to create the laser diode
Holograms or laser pointer Holograms and
that showed a real nice pattern of the
fringes
not very stable I mean there were times
when it was stable but every so often it
would sort of like draw a little bit of
a fit and the fringes would move where
they'd go away or do this and that and
it happened every so often you know the
fringes would come back in and seemed
really nice and then it would happen
again you know they'd start to drift
look you know
for 14.99 that's certainly to be
expected what was really interesting is
he also ordered a few other laser
pointers or laser diodes however you
want to turn them one of them was for a
gun sight on a gun
basically that's why it's called a gun
sight
for a handheld gun
and he said he was not able to ever get
a successful hologram using this gun
site so you know I reviewed the material
and it looked like a very nice setup
had a 635 nanometer diode a collimating
lens and provided a beautiful beam I
mean this beam looked cleaner than any
helium neon laser beam I've ever seen
come out of a tube and very sharp and
very nice looking beam
which you would think that this would be
able to create Holograms but I put it on
the interferometer and would you believe
we could not even get fringes
nothing
it was that bad
he also had a
I guess you would call it a module it
was the laser diode in housing
and it also had the chip sticking out of
the back of the laser diode housing with
two pigtail wires coming off of it that
you connected your battery to and we put
that up there as well and I don't know
if she tested I can't really remember
from the other day whether he said he
tested his making Holograms and wasn't
successful with it or not or whether he
even used it at all
there once again I put it on the
interferometer and there were fringes
but they were very light gray and in
fact if you didn't know what to look for
you wouldn't have seen or noticed the
fringes at all
which leads us to believe that it's not
always possible to use anything when it
comes to these diodes and diode modules
to make Holograms and you know to find
out what you can use and what you can't
use if someone all of a sudden decided
that they wanted to order that gun site
and try to make Holograms with it they'd
be completely out of luck because no
matter how hard I tried we could not
even get any any fringes at all with the
laser light now I don't know
whether this has anything to do with the
drive circuit or whether it's the diode
I imagine the 635 nanometer diode going
to be a 635 nanometer diode my guess and
this is just from working with them to
begin with and my guess is as good as
anyone else is out there on this as far
as this goes is that the answer
basically is in the drive circuitry I
don't think I think you could probably
take one of those diodes
and just hook it up to a more accurate
power supply driver and all of a sudden
you'd notice that you have fringes this
may be true this may not be true but
that's the feeling that I get
and
it's very important that you're deciding
to start with a laser diode holography
that you'd be very careful in what you
buy now we do know the infinitives work
very well for 14.99 I think he paid a
pretty hefty price for This Gun Site it
turns out it's not capable of making a
hologram at all
very interesting but I think a lot of
this has to do with the drive circuit
and it's quite possible now I know when
I was reading the instructions it said
that it actually had a an adjustable
potentiometer on their adjustable
resistor we could turn down the drive
current
I really should have turned that down a
little bit and you know
see if that helped because it may be
overdriving it
in order for it to be a gun sight and
you know cover as much distance as
possible it they may actually have that
variable resistor set so high that that
fringes infringes are just destroyed
when you put it onto a in a barometer
it's just it's just overdriving too much
so that that may be the problem right
there but who wants to go through all
that trouble
in any case just to show him what nice
fringes are like
I set up on the DNS laser that Sam and I
designed and put that on uniformitor and
he really almost fell in fact in fact he
fell over to the point of buying one
so unfortunately we're sold out of the
units but he's going to have one shipped
to him right after the New Year okay
moving on
um I have an announcement here from
Steve Michael and Steve is working on a
continuation of the shoebox holography
guide that I have and it's going to be
an advanced booklet where you can do and
actually the title is going to be
Advanced Techniques and laser pointer
holography and it's going to be built
around the shoebox holography system and
we're looking forward to that in fact
he's well he has some things on here
that I can say and some things he wants
to just keep a little one until things
are together in about four weeks but he
did do a master to copy that's an H1 H2
fiber optic technique using the shoebox
holography method of just the little
vibration isolation seat and you know
laser pointers and things of that nature
so yeah he's going to write up these
Advanced Techniques put them into a
little booklet and offer them on his
website and according to this email that
should be available in about four weeks
or so so you want to keep track of what
Steve is doing by visiting his website
at
www.qedimentary.com his website's also
listed right on the link page the
holography link page at my site if you'd
like to go over there and visit
so we'll be looking forward to seeing
that book come out and speaking of Steve
Michael I was just on the phone with him
earlier this evening and you know Steve
and I we've we've worked on this laser
pointer thing for for quite some time he
went off continuing his investigation
and different techniques techniques with
laser pointers I stayed with that for a
while and then moved on to uh working
with the higher power diode Ledger
lasers which eventually uh led to the
system Sam and I developed from some of
the
shortcomings that I found that both of
us found in the higher power laser
diodes
and you know Steve and I
we don't actually see things eye to eye
at times and we're going to put a show
together where we can both come on and
sort of like go back and forth a little
bit on how he thinks about certain
things how I think about certain things
like for instance Steve's real big on
split beam Holograms
I'm not I'm real big and I think the
future is going to be Advanced uh single
beam Holograms
but who knows what it's going to be but
you'll have an opportunity to come on
and hear both of us talk about it and
give our points and counterpoints on the
air hopefully maybe once a month where
we can both get together sort of like
Cisco on Ebert does with the movies only
we're going to do this with holography
and there's a number of different things
that Steve and I on opposite sides of
the coin with and this would be a nice
way for us to get together and real
really wrestle it out and sort of speak
and we'll do that on the air and you can
come on and tune in and listen to those
shows and should be a lot of fun
right Steve
all right got an email from Dr Salim
Valera
and this is very interesting here Steve
pay attention because this is about
single Beam work
um Dr Valera is a research scientist at
the Manchester Metropolitan University
in UK England and I'd like to read what
he wrote to Hall talk that he
would like to have or would like to
share with the holotalk listeners
hi Frank in your latest total talk you
gave several good reasons as to why
single beam holography is now preferable
over splitting techniques
as you know small green frequency
doubled and blue diode lasers are also
readily available on the market
it is only a matter of time before they
become affordable to the average
hobbyist
this opens up the possibilities of real
full color holography
trouble with three color transmission
Holograms recorded on a single Emulsion
is the crosstalk between the various
fringes
so if a master transmission whole gram
is recorded simultaneously with the red
green and blue beams and is then
illuminated for an image plane transfer
the red beam is diffracted by the blue
and green fringes as well as the red
fringes resulting in multiple images in
the transfer plane
this is not a problem with single Beam
with reflection Holograms due to their
strong bride selection properties once
the three beams have been suitably
combined the setup for full color
reflection Holograms is exactly the same
as for the single beam monochrome setup
further
if an image plane hologram is required
the image can be pulled forward using
the transfer technique described in your
whole talk the brag selection of the
wavelength again prevents crosstalk
I believe that full-color holography
will be within reach of most amateurs
within five years and that this is the
most important reason for perfecting the
single beam technique
I would like to hear your views regards
MMS Valera well I thank them very much
for sending this and uh
well I'll tell you what maybe the first
show that Steve and I do where we can go
back and forth we can have it as a
single Bean burst split beam
what will happen in the future points
and counterpoints so tune in tune into
that show I spoke with Steve earlier
tonight and he thought it was a good
idea too he's up for it he's game so to
speak
and
we hope that when we have our first show
available for you that you'll tune in
and also send us your comments on the
show as well
well that about wraps it up folks and
this is the end of 1999
I'm not going to get into whether it's
the end of the Millennium or not because
some people seem to think that it is and
some people seem to think that it isn't
but I will wish everyone a very happy
holiday season and also
a very Happy New Year
of course this is the last year of the
1900s I don't think anyone can argue
that so
um telegraphy is now moving into a new
age as well and if I've been able to do
anything to help it move forward and
continue in its growth I feel very
honored to do so and I feel also feel
very honored that you choose to tune
into the show each and every week as
well
I have a number of guests that are going
to be lined up starting with the whole
talk that will be providing the week of
January 9th
and I hope that you decide to come back
and listen until you go until Memorial
day of the year 2000 so this is Frank de
Freitas for whole talk thank you very
much for tuning in
and I will see you after the new year
take care God willing of course take
care